





Postdoc Researcher

BIO

I am a Uruguayan biologist (PhD) doing research in macroecology and biodiversity informatics. Currently, I am a postdoc researcher at the Czech University of Life Sciences (MOBI Lab), focused on the study of spatial and temporal patterns of biodiversity. I am also the founder of Biodiversidata (Uruguayan Consortium of Biodiversity Data), a member of the JULANA NGO, the admin for NaturalistaUY (the iNaturalist site for Uruguay), and a NatGeoExplorer.

EDUCATION

2013 – 2017	Ph.D., Life Sciences University of Lincoln, United Kingdom Evolution and Ecology Research Group, School of Life Sciences. Dissertation: Biodiversity in- formatics and macroecological patterns of biodiversity: Uruguay as a model region. Advisor: Daniel Pincheira-Donoso
2013 – 2015	M.Sc., Biological Sciences (Genetics) Department of Biodiversity and Genetics, Clemente Estable Biological Research Institute. Dissertation: Contributions of molecular ecology to the study of mammals in Uruguay. Advisors: Susana González and Mariana Cosse
2006 – 2012	B.Sc. (Hons), Biological Sciences Universidad de la República, Uruguay Department of Biodiversity and Genetics, Clemente Estable Biological Research Institute. Project: Development of molecular tools for the taxonomic identification of different carnivore species. Advisor: Mariana Cosse

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

PROFESSIONAL EXPE	RIENGE
04/2021 - present	Postdoc Czech University of Life Sciences (Czech Republic) Range dynamics of Neotropical carnivores in the MOBI Lab, Department of Spatial Sciences.
01/2021 - 04/2021	Intern UN Environmental Programme - World Conservation Monitoring Centre (Cambridge, UK) Knowledge Management internship in the Conserving Land and Seascapes Team
08/2018 - 12/2020 part time	Demonstrator Demonstrating for courses of Zoology, Paleontology, and Biological Anthropology at the School of Life Sciences
01/2017 - 07/2017 part time	Project Manager Co-coordination of the project 'Conservation in private protected areas of Uruguay'
11/2016 - 03/2017	Research Assistant Universidad de la República (Montevideo, Uruguay) Bioinformatics and genomics at the Department of Animal Genetics, School of Veterinary
10/2016 - 11/2016	Field Assistant Sampling plots of vascular plants for the project 'Rural Futures'
11/2015 - 10/2016 part time	Technician Livestock pedigree data management Rural Association of Uruguay (Montevideo, Uruguay)
11/2015 - 10/2016 part time	Research Assistant Universidad de la República (Montevideo, Uruguay) Bioinformatics and comparative genomics of Salmonella at the Institute of Hygiene, School of Medicine
01/2012 - 12/2015	Research Assistant Clemente Estable Biological Research Institute (Montevideo, Uruguay) Research and teaching at the Department of Biodiversity and Genetics
05/2012 - 04/2014 part time	Teaching Assistant Universidad de la República (Montevideo, Uruguay) Organization of outreach ativities at the Extension Unit, School of Science

PEER-REVIEWED ARTICLES

- 12. Pincheira-Donoso D., Harvey L.P., <u>Grattarola F.</u>, Winter M., Jara M., Cotter S.C., Tregenza T. & Hodgson D.J. (2021) The multiple origins of sexual size dimorphism in global amphibians. *Global Ecology and Biogeography*, 30(2): 443-458. [link]
- 11. <u>Grattarola F.</u>, Martínez-Lanfranco, J.A., ... & Pincheira-Donoso D. (2020) Multiple forms of hotspots of tetrapod biodiversity and the challenges of open-access data scarcity. *Scientific Reports*, 10(1): 1-15. [link]
- 10. <u>Grattarola F.</u>, Mai, P., ... & Pincheira-Donoso D. (2020) Biodiversidata: A novel dataset for the vascular plant species diversity in Uruguay. *Biodiversity Data Journal*, 8: e56850. [link]
- 9. <u>Grattarola F.</u> & Rodríguez-Tricot L. (2020) Mammals of Paso Centurión, an area with relicts of Atlantic Forest in Uruquay. *Neotropical Biology and Conservation*, 15(3): 267–283. [link]
- 8. D'Alessandro B., Pérez Escanda V., Balestrazzi V., <u>Grattarola F.</u>, ... & Betancor L. (2020) Comparative genomics of Salmonella enterica serovar Enteritidis ST-11 isolated in Uruguay reveals lineages associated with particular epidemiological traits. *Scientific Reports*, 10: 3638. [link]
- 7. <u>Grattarola F.</u>, Botto, G., ... & Pincheira-Donoso D. (2019) Biodiversidata: an open-access biodiversity database for Uruguay. *Biodiversity Data Journal*, 7: e36226. [link]
- 6. <u>Grattarola F.</u> & Pincheira-Donoso D. (2019) Data-sharing in Uruguay, the vision of collectors and data users. **Boletín de la Sociedad Zoológica del Uruguay**, 28(1): 1-14. [link]
- 5. Bergós L., <u>Grattarola F.</u>, Barreneche J.M., Herández D., & González S. (2018) Fogones de Fauna: an experience of participatory monitoring of wildlife in rural Uruguay. *Society & Animals*, 26(2), 171-185. [link]
- 4. Chouhy M., Santos C., Gaucher L., <u>Grattarola F.</u>, ... & Perazza, G. (2017) At the frontiers of knowledge: the quest for an integral training course on society-nature. *Integralidad Sobre Ruedas*, 4(1): 62–77. [link]
- 3. Cosse M., <u>Grattarola F.</u> & Mannise N. (2017) A novel real-time TaqMan[™]PCR assay for simultaneous detection of Neotropical fox species using noninvasive samples based on cytochrome C oxidase subunit II. *Mammal Research*, 62(4): 405-411. [link]
- 2. <u>Grattarola F.</u>, Hernández D., ... & Rodríguez-Tricot R. (2016) First record of jaguarundi (Puma yagouaroundi) (Mammalia: Carnivora: Felidae) in Uruguay, with comments about participatory monitoring. *Boletín de la Sociedad Zoológica del Uruguay*, 25(1): 85-91. [link]
- 1. <u>Grattarola F.</u>, Cosse M. & González S. (2015) A novel primer set for mammal species identification from feces samples. *Conservation Genetic Resources*, 7: 57–59. [link]

PRE-PRINT ARTICLES

- 2. <u>Grattarola F.</u>, Bowler E.D. & Keil P. (2022) Integrating presence-only and presence-absence data to model changes in species geographic ranges: An example of yaguarundí in Latin America. *EcoEvoRxiv*. [link]
- 1. Pincheira-Donoso D., Harvey L.P., Guirguis J., Goodyear L.E.B., Finn C., Johnson J.V., <u>Grattarola F.</u> (2022) Temporal and spatial patterns of vertebrate extinctions during the Anthropocene. *bioRxiv*. [link]

GRANTS, FUNDING

2022	Capacity Enhancement Support Programme £14,000 Project 'Extending knowledge on biodiversity Spanish-speaking community' CESP2021-007 [link]	Global Biodiversity Information Facility (GBIF) data quality and publication in the
2021 - 2022	Citizen Science for Species Discovery Grant £25,000 Project 'Naturalista UY – The iNaturalist comm	National Geographic Society unity for Uruguay' (Uruguay)
2019	College of Science Grant for Postgraduate Students £750 Attend the conference 'Biodiversity Next' (Leiden,	University of Lincoln The Netherlands)
2019	Travel Grant for Postgraduate Students £500 Attend the course 'Advancing in statistical mode ecologists using R' (Glasgow, Scotland)	University of Lincoln elling for evolutionary biologists and
2018	Mobility Fund for Postgraduate Research Students £500 Deliver the 'First meeting of the members of Biodi	Santander - University of Lincoln iversidata' (Montevideo, Uruguay)

2018	Travel Grant for Early Career European Researchers & Scientists £1,500 Attend the '11th RDA Plenary Meeting' (Berlin, Germany)	
2017 - 2020	Ph.D. International FellowshipNational Agency for Research and Innovation (ANII)£49,000 Postgraduate Fellowship POS_EXT_2016_1_136663 (Lincoln, United Kingdom)	
2017	Travel Grant for Postgraduate Students Centro Brasileiro-Argentino de Biotecnologia (CBAB/CABBIO) £1,800 Attend the Course 'Bioinformatics Tools for RNA-Sequence Data Analysis' at Laboratório Nacional de Computação Científica (Petrópolis, RJ, Brasil)	
2015	Internship Grant for Postgraduate Students Association of Universities of the Montevideo Group (AUGM) £1,500 Internship stay at the Laboratório de Biodados, Universidade Federal de Minas Gerais (UFMG) (Belo Horizonte, Brazil)	
2013	Internship Grant for Postgraduate Students Program for the Development of Basic Sciences (PEDECIBA) £1,500 Internship stay at Bioinformatics at the Department of Biochemistry and Molecular Biology, University of Mississippi (Starkville, United States)	
2013 – 2015	Posgraduate National Fellowship \$8,500 Postgraduate Fellowship POS_NAC_2012_1_8976 (Montevideo, Uruguay)	
2012	Travel Grant £1,500 Attend the 'VIII Genetic Workshop for Conservation: new tools and new concepts' (Chillán, Chile)	
2012	Mobility Grant Association of Universities of the Montevideo Group (AUGM) £2,000 A semester at Universidade Estadual de Jaboticabal (UNESP) (Jaboticabal, SP, Brazil)	
2011 - 2012	Posgraduate National Fellowship National Agency for Research and Innovation (ANII) £2,000 Initiation in Research Fellowship BE_INI_2010_1961 (Montevideo, Uruguay)	

STUDENTS

Enzo Cavalli, BSc (Honours) in Biological Sciences, School of Science, **Universidad de la República**. Project: 'Effects of livestock on the mammal community of Paso Centurión, Cerro Largo'. Advisor, finished in 2019. [thesis]

Rodrigo Montiel, BSc (Honours) in Biological Sciences, School of Science, **Universidad de la República**. Project: 'NaturalistaUY as a community science tool to improve biodiversity knowledge in Uruguay'. Advisor, ongoing.

LECTURING

2017 – 2019 two editions	Modern Mammals Lecture in the graduate course of Palaeontolo Fariña [slides]	School of Science, Universidad de la República (Uruguay) ogy, for 15-20 students. Invited by Dr. Richard
2018	Management and analysis of camera trap rec Course for NGOs, researchers and governme reneche and Gabriel Perazza [syllabus]	cords using R Ministry of Environment (Uruguay) nt people. Taught together with Juan M. Bar-
2016 – 2017 two editions	Introduction to Python Lecture at posgraduate course 'Introduction to command line and programming for bioinformatic analysis', for 25-30 students in Biological Sciences. Invited by Dr. Andris Iriarte [syllabus]	
2013 – 2017 four editions	·	Universidad de la República, Uruguay ology, Biology, Geography and Social Sciences. aks, Magdalena Chouhy, Andrea Garay, Lucía
2014	Environmental education and community inv Lecture at posgraduate course 'Conservation be Invited by Dr. Susana González.	volvement Universidad de la República, Uruguay iology' for 15-20 students in Biological Sciences.
2014	Introduction to Biology Discussion group for the course Introduction t dents of Biological Sciences. Taught together	Universidad de la República, Uruguay to Biology School or 15-20 undergraduate stu- with Dr. Juan Cristina.

SERVICE FOR JOURNALS

Biodiversity Data Journal.
Global Ecology and Biogeography

Journal of Biogeography

CITATION METRICS

Google Scholar (06/2022) 77 citations, h-index = 5

ACADEMIC MEMBERSHIPS

2021 – International Biogeography Society.

2020 – GBIF Biodiversity Open Data Ambassador.

2019 - Organization for Women in Science for the Developing World (OWSD).

2018 - British Ecological Society (BES).

2018 - Research Data Alliance (RDA) - SHARC Interest Group.

2013 – Interdisciplinary Group on Society-Nature Relationships (RETEMA).

Montevideo, Uruguay

2012 – Latin American Network for Conservation Genetics (REGENEC).

2010 - Zoological Society of Uruguay (SZU).

TALKS

- 2022 How Open Science activities are perceived and recognised in Research and the Research career seoul, Korea Grattarola F.*, Shmagun H., Mabile L. & Cambon-Thomsen A. / International Data Week 2022 RDA Plenary Breakout [conference]
- 2021 As a naturalist in my country, where are there more opportunities to fill in information gaps? Online Grattarola F.* & Barreneche J.M. / LatinR Conference [code repo]
- 2021 **Roundtable: Activism through digital media**<u>Grattarola F.*</u> / 4th Conference on Digital Citizenship [video]

2021 **The value of open education policies to promote environmental education**Grattarola F.* / CILAC Latin American Open Science Forum [video]

- 2020 **Hotspots of biodiversity and the challenges of open-data scarcity**Online Invited Grattarola F.* / Seminar of the Department of Spatial Sciences, Czech University of Life Sciences Prague
- 2019 **Biodiversity hotspots in Uruguay: real or fabricated?**Grattarola F.* & D. Pincheira-Donoso / British Ecological Society Annual Meeting [slides]
 Belfast, Northern Ireland
- 2019 **Biodiversidata:** a collaborative initiative towards open data availability in Uruguay

 Leiden, The Netherlands

 Grattarola F.* & D. Pincheira-Donoso / Biodiversity Next Conference [abstract]
- 2019 Biodiversity data in Uruguay: a long way to go Leiden, The Netherlands
- Invited Grattarola F.* / Biodiversity Informatics 101 Workshop at Biodiversity Next Conference

 2019 Biodiversity hotspots in Uruguay

 Lincoln, United Kingdom
- Grattarola F.* & D. Pincheira-Donoso / School of Life Sciences Postgraduate Symposium, University of Lincoln

 iNaturalist as a tool to enhance the conservation of biodiversity in Uruguay

 Maldonado, Uruguay (online)
- Grattarola F.* / Rufford Conference Uruguay [video]

 2017 Landscape genetics of the crab-eating fox Cerdocyon thous (Carnivora: Canidae) Montevideo, Uruguay
 Grattarola F.*, Bartesaghi L., Hernández D., Soutullo A., Mannise N., González S. & Cosse M. / IV Uruguayan Zo-
- 2016 **Humans and fauna in Paso Centurión (Cerro Largo) from an interdisciplinary perspective** La Paloma, Uruguay Chouhy M.*, Garay A., Bergós L., Gaucher L., Perazza G., <u>Grattarola F.</u> & Santos C. / III Interdisciplinary Conference
- 2016 **Democratization of information in the context of territorial management**Gaucher L.*, Hernández D., <u>Grattarola F.</u>, Rodriguez-Tricot L., Duarte A., Perazza G. & González, S. / III Interdisciplinary Conference on Biodiversity and Ecology
- 2016 Molecular detection of species and sex determination in road killed foxes in Uruguay

 Mannise N.*, Cosse M., Grattarola F., Repetto L. & González S. / First Ibero-American Congress on Biodiversity and Road Infrastructure

SCI COMM

- 2022 Divulgación científica comunitaria con JULANA y NaturalistaUY
 - Radio interview by Diego Varela and Fernanda Cabrera for Radio Fénix [video]
- 2022 Scientific Pokemon Go

ology Congress

on Biodiversity and Ecology

Podcast episode by Soledad Machado for Medios Públicos [episode]

2020 Biodiversidata began to digitize the herbarium of the National Museum of Natural History

Press note by Leo Lagos for La Diaria [article]

2021 iNaturalist - What is it and what can it do for our project?

Talk with students of the Polo Educativo Tecnológico Arrayanes (Park Rangers) [slides]

2020 Getting started with iNaturalist - Project RACATÚ

Online talk with primary school students from rural school N102 of Berachi (Cerro Largo, Uruquay) [slides]

2020 Uruguayans are wanted to participate in a platform that helps scientists

Press note by Analía Filosi for Diario El País [article]

2019 iNaturalist: a bet on citizen science

Talk at Museum of Natural History Torres de la Llosa [slides]

2019 iNaturalist a citizen science tool to improve biodiversity knowledge in Uruguay

Radio interview by Juan Vique in Radio Uruguay [radiocut]

2019 The Uruguayan Consortium of Biodiversity Data, Biodiversidata, published the first open data set

Press note by Leo Lagos for La Diaria [article]

2019 Series 'Gender and IT' - Pan Ceibal

Online talk with students from Canelones, Paysandú, Tacuarembó and Treinta y Tres' primary schools in Uruguay

2019 Biodiversidata: Biodiversity Open Data

Online talk at the Third Edition of 'Datos y Cogollos: Open Data in Uruguay'. La Diaria Media Lab (Montevideo, Uruguay)

2019 Exhibition 'A Computer of One's Own'

Art exhibition about pioneer women in Computer Science at CSSconf and JSConf (Berlin, Germany) [project]

2018 Big data in biodiversity

Radio interview with Federico Weinstein in the science segment of the program Justicia Infinita, Radio Océano (93.9 FM) (Montevideo, Uruguay)

2017 The Marsh Seedeater

Video production for PROBIDES organization [video]

2016 Drawn news: First record of a jaguarundi in Uruguay

Video production for JULANA NGO [video]

REFERENCES

Petr Keil Czech University of Life Sciences, Czech Republic

keil@fzp.czu.cz | phone +420 776 371 840

Daniel Pincheira-Donoso Queen's University Belfast, UK

d.pincheira-donoso@qub.ac.uk | phone +44(0) 28 9097 2967

Lauren Weatherdon UN Environment Programme World Conservation Monitoring Centre, UK

lauren.weatherdon@unep-wcmc.org | phone +420 776 371 840

Susana González Clemente Estable Biological Research Institute, Uruguay

sugonza9@yahoo.com | phone +598 24861417